People are scared. They
lost faith in the government.
They have no trust.
to power. They
begin
to organize,
mobilize and
to take the law into one's own hands
hands. I was limited.
Prime Minister,
which is not really
wanted to stop the boats.
He adheres
very liberal
views on migration,
so I didn't want to
reduce
immigration. He was
indifferent to the stop
boats. I mean
that he somehow
privately asked
me, why so many
people are upset
through boats? These people
come here and
are working. This is good.
for the economy.
Did Rishi Sunak say this?
Of course, yes. He
told me this when
was chancellor.
When Rishi Sunak was
Chancellor, he said
: "I don't understand why
people are upset because
boats. These people
come here and
are working".
Yes.
Oho. This episode
sponsored by our
friends from Hillsdale-
college. At once
after this episode
check out their
incredible online
courses that are
absolutely
free of charge on
Hillsdale.edu/trigger. Therefore,
Suella Braverman,
Welcome
back to Triggernometry.
Greetings.
Er...
Glad to be back.
It's very nice of you.
returned.
Last time, of course.
, you came to the show
shortly after,
how they ceased to be,
let's say so,
Minister of the Interior
Rishi Sunak's affairs.
Yes.
Uh, and since then
A lot has happened,
in particular you wrote
book, so we are happy and
We are eager to see you.
Uh, but come on.
let's talk first
about your history
families in the book. Uh, and,
you know, the question "
"Where are you from?" which we,
maybe we'll touch
later. Uh, but
interesting for us,
of course, for ours too
the audience would be that
that, leaving
conservative government
at that time, you still
were a member
Conservative
party, and I remember,
How did you put one or the other?
two are a little sharper
question, and you
responded very well
diplomatically.
Since then, of course, you
left
Conservative Party
. You have joined "
Reforms". So what are you
can you tell
us about why
conservative government
failed this country, that,
I think
generally recognized,
including herself
Conservative Party
now, what are you talking about?
could have said then.
Yes. Well, that's very
nice introduction, so
what am I really
wrote this book for
all those people,
including myself,
which are frankly
angry at
last
conservative government
and the last one
Labour government,
but the most recent
conservative government,
for the harm they caused
inflicted on this country. AND
now that I am older
not in the Conservative
parties, I am free
to speak honestly against
uh, what I think
institutional
cowardice and deceit,
frankly speaking. I
repeatedly
said this
within the party,
when she was a minister
internal affairs;
when she hugged a tall
public office,
being
the most influential
a woman in government,
trying, uh,
to force
conservative government
to do the right thing
regarding small boats,
visas, Islamism,
anti-Semitism on
our streets, uh, and
he, he refused
again and again.
What exactly?
Conservative Party
, the last prime minister
minister from
Conservatives, members
cabinet of ministers
from conservatives. AND
by this I mean
Rishi Sunaka, Jeremy
Ganta, Kemi Badenoch,
Tom Tugengat.
Many of these people,
who still rule
Conservative
party. And therefore in
to my book I
actually said that,
you know, from David
Cameron to Teresa
May, Boris Johnson,
Rishi Sunaka, Kemi
Badenoch is different
face, but the same
tactics, the same
deception, the same
way of doing things, the same
family. You know,
to give loud
promises, abuse
rhetoric, but to do
very little, and in fact
to let people down.
Recently we have
show was journalist Dan
Hodges. I believe that
it was wonderful
discussion, he brought
some interesting thoughts,
but one aspect that
both of us and Francis
quite strong
upset, —this
the issue of small boats.
And let's be frank,
this question now becomes
problem number one,
apart from the economy, which,
of course, also huge
, for many people in
this country, not just
for representatives
right-wing marginals.
You could say this
became mainstream. THERE ARE-
uh, and there was a feeling that
regardless of whether
what we always said
sounded like: "Oh, this
too difficult, this
too confusing, you
you can't do this
make". What are you,
you say we should
invade, you
You know, that's all.
other. You, as a minister
internal affairs,
tried something
make. You...without
insult, but you suffered
failures like everyone else
.
I'm being honest about this.
Yes.
This is undeniable.
Why is this so complicated?
question? Because, well,
this can be very
simplified, I just
ordinary person,
maybe it's very
simple way
formulate, but I
I think about it like this. IN
any other time in
stories, if there were dozens
thousands of men, and this
exactly what
is happening,
arrived at your
countries—some said
would, would invade
your country, you know,
we can talk about it
argue. Tens
thousands of people
arrived by boat to
your island
state. King
countries organized
a detachment of armed men
people to leave
there and stopped it. IN
any period
history is
would be perceived as
rational
respond. I'm not saying
what should we do
it's today, but I
I'm just stating that
throughout history
border protection
was considered almost the only
the duty of the state, and
definitely—his
the main task.
How did we end up in
situations where even
people like you who
at least they want it
can't do
to do this?
Um, it's because of marriage.
political will. So
I was almost the only one.
Minister of the Interior
affairs, which really
wanted to stop the boats
and had that in mind. And that
what I encountered, and
the reason why I
failed,
consisted in the fact that
tied me up
the prime minister, who
I didn't really want to.
stop the boats,
Minister of Finance,
who didn't want it, and
the whole office
ministers, to whom
lacked political
of will. And it becomes very
Of course, and that's it,
What am I talking about frankly?
I declare: all this was
just a show. Therefore,
it all came down to
loud conversations. You
you know, showing off and
disclosure of this
harsh rhetoric.
Performance. But
actually for
behind the scenes, behind
behind closed doors,
completely lacking
the necessary will to
to do the right thing with
legal,
political and
diplomatic points
vision.
What is the answer to this?
Yes, well, tell us,
because Dan Hodges says that
this is impossible
solve.
Well, he's wrong.
Okay, so how is it?
solve?
fully exists
way to solve this. AND
you can
to make sure of
examples of success
other countries, what is this
was stopped in others
states. So, what
need to be done—and
This is what I am useless with.
tried
to reach Rishi
Sunaka, Kemi Badenoch
and almost everyone in
Conservative
parties—this
first of all, get out of
European
human rights conventions
human. I understand that
I sound like a seasoned person.
disc. But I will
continue
to say it while it is
will not be done,
because I saw—no
only as a minister
internal affairs, but also
earlier than
Attorney General
, and even earlier as a lawyer,
who worked in
immigration courts
before it became
deputy, -like ours
rights laws
human
were used
against the British
the people and, in particular,
state. So every time,
when the minister
internal affairs
wants to delay
illegal
migrant or
deport him,
she is facing
infinite
number of legal
lawsuits, many of
which are fabricated,
but mostly
are based on
human rights, namely
on article 3
European
human rights conventions
human. This is a ban.
torture,
inhuman and
humiliating
dignity, behavior.
So, the migrant
arrives at the Great
Britain with evil
intentions, perhaps with
Afghanistan by boat.
We are trying it.
deport. He says
: "Article 3, if you
send me
back, even to
France, not to mention
about Afghanistan,
you are violating mine
the human right to
protection from torture,
because in Afghanistan
me just
"They will torture me." And he
can invent some
political party, to
which he seems to be
belongs to. He can
to invent some
conditional oppressor
or a complaint that may
to exist in
Afghanistan. But in
Iran, if they are from
Iraq, if they are from
Eritrea - Eritrea
is now a country
choice. If you
come and declare,
that you are from Eritrea, you
guaranteed to win
appeal in the courts. So
article 3 often
used as
way to stay in
Great Britain and
to undermine the ability
state to
deportation. Article 8—
this is another problem
European
human rights conventions
human. This is the right to
private life. Therefore,
someone can
to be here. It
maybe, you know,
foreign criminal,
someone who arrived
here, raped,
killed or traded
drugs. And we
arrest them and
we condemn for
violation of our
laws. We plant them
to prison. But we
we say, "Hey, this
a person from Jamaica". "We
we want to deport
them back to Jamaica." And
they say: "Article 8,
you can't me
deport, because in
I have a child." "I have
6 months ago
a child was born in
Great Britain". "
So, if you
send me to
Jamaica, you are violating
my human right to
family life". And, as
as a rule, it becomes
a winning argument
in the courts. And therefore this
Convention on the Rights of
a person who
started with
noble aspirations
and contains words from
which no one
will argue,
the right to life. I am not
against the right to life.
I am not against the law—
prohibition of torture. I
agree with the right to
fair trial.
was distorted,
stretched and
expanded during
many years, yes
what is she really like
became a charter for
illegal
migrants, not
a document that
protects the healthy
sense,
justice and
human dignity.
So explain this to me,
Suella, because
last time when
we talked about it, and
since then in your
comments, and
today you say,
what was missing
political will, Rishi
Sunak, other members
Conservative
parties. And the central
the argument of the book, as I
I understand him—
Correct me if
I am mistaken, —it lies
in that our governments
and the state apparatus,
such as Whitehall,
refuse
engage in
immigration, because
consider it a way
manipulation
economic
statistics, right? But
this does not apply
illegal
immigration, and that's exactly
the moment that I
never could
understand this
argument. What
justification for that
that Rishi Sunak, Boris
Johnson or anyone
the other did not go that way
the way you
offered? After all, this
cannot apply
economy, right?
This is something else. So what?
is happening?
That's right. Regarding the question
ECHR, I was the first
Minister-
a conservative who
In office in 2022
general
the prosecutor publicly
stated: if we
we want to stop
boats, we need
withdraw from the ECHR. Can
it would be thought,
based on your
the question is what if this
there was a decision, and I
said it as a matter of fact
Attorney General
and former lawyer,
who defended
Ministry
internal affairs in
cases about
immigration, then this
would have some weight, and
people like Rishi
Sunak or Kemi Badenoch
, would say: "Yes,
maybe we should do this
make". Why are they
yes, you know, fiercely
refused?
Opposition to this
within
Conservative
the party was really
very, very strong. IN
2022, 23 and even 24 years
my words about that
we need to get out of
ECHR, were considered
marginal opinion.
Why? This is a repetition.
debates on
Brexit. These are the same ones
arguments. Well, they say,
way out of this
international
the convention will be
diplomatically
harmful to
reputation of the Great
Britain abroad.
You will put us in
on a par with Russia, which
, you know, kicked out of
Council of Europe. We are not
we want to be in one
group with Russia. You
destroy
civil liberties
. How dare you say,
that we can get out of
ECHR? We are respectful
a country that is proud
protection
civil liberties
. So, these are the same ones
false arguments that
easy to refute,
but they are constantly
repeat
supporters
maintaining membership,
liberal
establishment that
constitutes a significant
part
Conservative
parties to speak
against withdrawing from the ECHR. AND
it was…they
won in this
disputes. I lost.
this dispute
within
Conservative
parties. And you know, exactly
so I left
Conservative Party
because they ultimately do not
agree with this
politics. They only
superficially they say that
changed their mind.
Three years later,
you know, they
caught up with me, and
Kemi said, "Oh,
actually, maybe
Suella was right, and
we should copy
this policy because it
seems enough
popular, Reform about
they said that, but
Nigel says this
for years". So let's
just copy it and
let's hope,
that no one will notice,
that we really don't
we mean this.
But the truth is that
vast majority
Tory MPs
categorically against
exit from
European
human rights conventions
person for those reasons,
which I posted. And you
you know, this is another one
big lie to the Tories.
You know, I'm for
people had different opinions
on various issues and
opposed
policy for reasons
rationality,
principles or
expediency, but it
terrible arguments, or
wrong?
Right. I agree.
But they were
convincing and
remain the same
among liberals
elites inside
Conservative
parties.
Why do you allow...U
we are in the country now
could be up to a million
illegal
immigrants, and this
number constantly
is growing. This is not
good reasons
in order for this to happen
was happening. It
It's just not right.
They would all say...I
countless
argued with
my colleagues-
conservatives, with
people like Kemi
Badenoch, from Rishi
Sunak. And I
I am retelling my
conversations with Rishi
Sunak. I said: "
Listen, Rishi, we
we are lagging behind in
surveys. You can
to call an election
next year or
in a year. We have this
boat crisis. It
the main problem,
through which people
angry. You must
act decisively." And he
like this: "Yes, I know, I
I want to do this.
priority. Therefore I
I'm making up a slogan:"
We will do everything possible,
"Let's stop the boats." I
I am seeing you off.
press conferences. IN
I like these spectacular
stands and all sorts
events, and I constantly
I get into this
headlines". And I said
: "Well, you have to act.
You must act decisively.
. And you know, if you are
you decide, maybe you
you will win the following
elections, because this is an issue
life and death". But
to fix this, you
must do
necessary, even if
difficult steps. You
You have to withdraw from the ECHR. You
you have to provide it again
to the British state
powers
to delay for
border and
deport. If
withdraw from the ECHR, plan
regarding Rwanda will work.
The main reason why
we could not
send those planes
from the first time—this
ECHR. This happened.
through judges
European Court of Justice
human rights in
Strasbourg, which at 11 o'clock
in the evening when the planes
were already standing on the runway
runway,
issued a prescription and
They said, "No,
stop these flights.
Stop Rwanda
program. And it became
a fatal blow to
Rwandan scheme.
If we hadn't been
member of this court, those
airplanes could
fly up. And we would
started the whole thing
Rwandan program with
ready-made housing and
Rwandans,
ready with us
to cooperate. I
went there to
to see the buildings that
were built for
placement of these
illegal
migrants. This is quite
humane, recognized by the UN
program. All this was
fatally thwarted, because
we were prevented by laws
about human rights, which
used in
courts of the Great
Britain and
Strasbourg Court.
And I told him: "We
"must do it."
And he replied: "Well,
you know, that would be...we
we don't want to break
international law." It
too...that's too much
radically. This is too much.
dangerously. And under this
he meant that in
the party is too Tory,
including himself,
who just didn't want to
to spoil what is well-established.
We are having this conversation,
Suella, we use
the words "radical",
we say "
dangerous". But I
I tell you now: in
real world
many people already
radicalized, and
the situation is very
dangerous because they
constantly demanded not
only a decrease in level
immigration, but also
termination
illegal
immigration. This is not
is happening. We
we see this in others too
aspects when people
take the law into their own hands
hands. And I'm worried about that.
that many people say: "
Yes, I agree with them,
"friend." And this,
sorry, it's on
responsibility
government. This is on
Conservative
government, and this is
responsibility
Labor
government.
Right. People already
at the limit of patience.
They are on the edge, and I
I'm really afraid for
public order,
because you are right: people
lost faith in what
their governments will decide
this crisis. They see,
what's happening today
per day, and this
is spreading. In mine
electoral district
Fareham and
Waterlooville
illegal migrants
arrived in Portsmouth,
right on the outskirts. We
we can see
the embankment from my
district. Fortnight
so it was Portsmouth.
Last week it was
Gosport. This is no longer
limited to Kent
and Dover. It's everywhere.
People see the consequences
in their communities
through hotels for
refugees, when women
and girls experience
attacks from
illegal
migrants. I
visited Pittington
a few weeks ago and
met with women,
which literally
lost sleep over
perspective
settlement over
thousands of illegals
migrants conscript
age on the outskirts of this
small
rural village in
Oxfordshire. So people
scared. They
lost faith in the government.
They have no trust.
to power, and you are right,
they start
to self-organize
, mobilize and
to take the law into one's own hands
hands. And you know when
we are getting to this
moment, I really
I'm afraid for
public safety, and
, as I already said, for
public order.
I don't remember which one.
just yesterday
week, but it seems
over 700 illegal
migrants arrived in
this country. And then
In one day.
In one day. And I see,
both on the internet and
among familiar people,
what degree of tension
really begins
grow. And mine
question: when the government
Will he finally wake up?
Because this situation,
Let's be honest, just
will escalate.
That's right. She only
is getting worse. It
because the numbers are still
...you know, the government says: "
Oh, well, there are fewer arrivals.
than last year."
As you say, boats
are getting bigger,
number of people per
day still
incredibly high, and
the threat is getting closer
to our homes.
Therefore, I believe that people
are becoming more and more
more furious because of it. Them
It's getting scary. They
scared and angry.
And I'm scared, and I
actually too
angry. And having...
You know, I was
Minister of the Interior
things, and I don't have
no trust in
government. I don't have any.
Conservative
party, not before
Labour
government that they
will they have the will or not
ability is
to fix. And therefore,
You know, I understand.
why are people scared and
why are they angry.
Most workwear
—it is a cotton blend,
sewn in the shape of pants,
which is called
functional. It
works until you
need to be active
move, or until
it will rain, or while you
don't try
to feel a pocket, which
not where it should be.
Truework creates
overalls that really
designed for
such conditions. Workers
T2 pants are stretched in
four directions,
so you can
to bend, to stand on
knees and
to rise, not
feeling resistance
fabrics.
Water repellent
cover to keep out the rain
ruined your morning, and
nine pockets exactly
where they are needed
professionals, not
where someone is
came up with. You are not
It would surprise me if I said,
that I'm not quite the same
a man who works
hands. The closest thing that
I do—I watch,
like someone else
is fixing my boiler.
Very satisfactory. So
I will allow reviews.
say everything for me.
Matthew Hobbes says that
until now
could never find
so comfortable, strong and
pants that are so great
are sitting. CJ Argo
says: they came
perfect, as soon as I get them
dressed. And Dan S.
simply says: "Comfortable,
wear-resistant, excellent
"pocket location"
. Truework workwear
checked during
10 years of people who
working in real
conditions with
tools.
Work is not
stops only
because the weather
is changing. Choose
T2 work trousers and
feel yourself
comfortable, no matter what
brought the day.
Get 15% off
my first
order on truework.com
with the code trigg. This is true.
k dot com code trigg.
Truework, created so,
as if it's important because it
Indeed.
But also, Sewell,
when will it come
the moment when we
let's actually do it
for this, because yes
It can't go on.
At some point
metaphorical rubber
will meet with
on the road, and that's when
everything will be true
alarming.
Yes. Well, that's why, I
I mean, this
the reason why I
joined the
of the Reform party. I
I mean, I
lost any
belief in Conservative
party. I never
could believe
none of theirs
word. So, the only
party that has
authority and what was
consistent in this
and other issues, —
This is "Reform". AND
Nigel spoke for himself.
about withdrawing from the ECHR, well,
you know, a lot,
much earlier than
I. He is the one who pointed out
to the disaster with
mass migration 10
years ago during
referendum on Brexit.
He stood before that
with a poster and said that
they are on the verge of
influx of legal
migrants. For all this
courage, you know,
he was called
all sorts of bad
things. His physical
attacked, he
ostracized and
demonized
mainstream media and
establishment. But he
never backed down
from the fight for
truth for
of the British people.
And so I finally,
Thank God, I have "
Reform. I finally
found a political
a house where I can
believe in this
question.
And the last question,
which one I want to put
on this occasion: they
are arriving from France.
Why don't we
we are talking to
the French government?
Why don't we say: "
Listen, we
need to find
some kind of solution." "Why
they just float
here, and the French,
it seems quite
satisfied, if not
to say that secretly
encourage this?
You are right. So,
except for legislative
changes, withdrawal from the ECHR and
providing our
immigration
to officers of greater
powers that
possible only after
withdrawal from the ECHR, we
also needed
diplomatic solution
. And this is cooperation,
true collaboration with
by the French. And again
Yes, I'm telling you.
book like me
communicated and begged
his French
colleague at the time,
Gerald Darmanen,
Minister of the Interior
affairs of France. I
told him: "This is a win
for both sides, for
for you and for me. If
you intercepted
boats if you
really seriously
were concerned about safety
borders on
north coast
France,
intercepted,
detained and
controlled
illegal
migrants, it would be
a victory not only for
us in the Great
Britain, but also for you,
because these thousands
migrants are headed to
Calais and Pas-de-Calais region
Kale, because they want
to reach Dover. And this
destroyed that
region in the north
France.
Municipal government
angry at
the French government, because
not enough is being done
. There reigns
criminality. There are
large camps. Camps
in Sangatta actually
still exist. It
really did harm
area. It
damaged tourism,
rural
economy and
security. If this
the route was
blocked, these people
would stop going to
northern region
France, you would just
blocked this path.
So, that would be
success for you. It
win-win
version. Unfortunately, me too
I think this is an echo.
Brexit times,
the French government does not
was and still is not
seriously
tuned to
problem solving
illegal migration
in the north of its
countries. I was told,
which, honestly, for
it's not them
political
priority. Their
priority in matters
illegal migration
—this is southern
coast, their
southern border with
Italy. They are more
concerned about the influx
illegal
migrants from Italy to
south of France. AND
after all, if they
are leaving France, this
it is quite convenient for them
.
This is exactly what I'm talking about.
was going to you
to ask. If you don't
you can close the entrance,
maybe you will open
Entrance.
This is it now
takes place in
France.
They send
these people to us, because we don't
can stop
their influx.
Yes. Yes, and, you know, we
we continue to pay
they are hundreds of millions
pounds, we will continue
we spend this money
on the French.
It seems like every month we
we conclude new agreements,
promising more
drones over the English Channel,
intelligence sharing, and
that it will stop the boats.
All this has no
makes sense, because the French
don't really want to
to solve this
problem. And because
Macron holds a grudge
on the British after
Brexit, and it definitely
had a grudge against Boris
Johnson and any
conservative government,
because I thought
conservatives
responsible for
Brexit. But exactly
therefore, again, no
I know, have you seen it?
was achieved
agreement between
Nigel Farage and
By Jordan Bardella.
Jordan Bardella,
most likely, it will be
part of the following
the French government, and
Bardella and his
the party really
recognize the destructive
the impact of illegal
migration in France,
they see the real
the need for
a true Frenchman
British
cooperation in the English Channel,
to stop this. And I
I think that between
Bardella and Farage
there is a real one
devotion, even if
political, not
legal.
So I want to touch
the topic you
commented; actually,
I also spoke in
podcasts with Fraser
Nelson about what
Rishi Sunak is not
Englishman, and all that
turned into
big public
discussion. But I
I think these things
related because
mass level
migration, which we
had, forced us to
this, as well as
identical policy,
which we conducted
the last two
decades where
everyone was encouraged
to think of oneself as
about part of your
community. You know,
you are British
Asian, I am British
Eastern European, and
France, obviously,
Venezuelan, like everyone else
They know, right? So we
all members of a certain
community, instead of
to be simple
by the British. And here it is
now we have waves
mass immigration,
demographic share
indigenous
British
population significantly
decreased,
especially in large
cities, so they
feel a little
less protected,
you can say. I would
said, even significantly
less protected. You
have an implant
identity. And therefore
now we are forced
to discuss about
what does it mean to be
in English, which means
to be British. And I
said that Rishi Sunak
not English, because
he is British
Asian, which is true.
He is British and Asian.
. And you, you might say,
came to my defense, and
you also talk about
it's in your book. Or
can you just
explain this to people, because
survey, probably
against us. Apparently,
most people if
look at
polls, they say,
that anyone can be
English, if he
was born here, that
may be true, but
Maybe not, I don't know.
Well, it seems some
people literally don't
know who we are. AND
I think you are right,
this is a consequence
experiment with
mass immigration.
And the feeling
cohesion,
feeling of unity
identity has become
harder to determine. THERE ARE
Britishness, with
on the one hand, which
actually deserves
very serious
discussion, what are we talking about
not quite here
we are talking. But how
we are related to
Britishness in this
country, it's a scandal.
Anyone can be
British. This became
simply
administrative
formality. You
you come here as
low-skilled
migrant on the wave
Boris. You earn
, working in the black
market, perhaps
Have you lived here for a few years?
years. You can
submit fairly quickly
application for receipt
citizenship
Britain, and it will be very
few obstacles for
to become
citizen. None
questions about whether
Do you love this country?
Did you make yours?
contribution, are you
culturally
answer
Britain. Compare
this with other countries,
where much
Go easy
treat their own
citizenship. Japan,
Singapore. To become
Singaporean, you
must be very
a wealthy person
, which made a significant
contribution to the economy
Singapore. And only
then, if you're lucky,
you will get this
special status
Singaporean. Same
and in other countries. But
here—everything is allowed
for everyone. Then in
we have a problem
Englishness. And I am with
I agree with you. I quote
you in my book,
because the discussion that
you called, was
enough for me
interesting. I never
seriously, not about this
I was thinking. I
never put it
in doubt. I grew up with
their parents,
with my family, and we
never called
themselves as English. AND
my parents and ours
social circle
never called
themselves as English. And I
himself an Englishman. It
feels very
unnatural. For me
strange, incomprehensible and
it is wrong to say,
that I am English. I am from
I am happy to say that I
British. And I,
obviously,
Indian
ethnic origin
. It seems that's accurate.
and a graph in the form
census that I can
to mark. And I never
didn't put it under
doubt until you
pointed this out. AND,
you know, it caused
a wave of liberalism
hysteria. And I think that
I can say one thing:
when Rishi is not with you
I agree, this is usually
a sign that you are on
the right path.
You know, he seems
not a bad guy.
Isn't he pretty?
boy?
He is very good.
boy, yes. With him
you can drink tea, but
as prime minister
he is hopeless.
Well, that's interesting, isn't it?
Yes? And it seems to me,
he is trying to be
to those who embody
all these good intentions.
Yes.
But I don't think he
really understands
the discussion that is here
is being sharpened.
Agree.
And I think that
the discussion is
because there are many white people
Englishmen—no one
wants to say this
publicly, but
privately they say
—feel that they
the only ones who don't
allowed to have
own identity.
Certainly.
And I don't understand why
continue
insist on this.
It seems very good to me.
an unwise act.
He personifies
liberal trend,
cosmopolitan elites
, which constitute
basis
Conservative
parties. And I don't
surprised that he
He says so. He
adheres to very
liberal views
on migration, therefore not
wanted to shorten it.
He was
ambiguous about
boat stops. I have
meaning that he
once privately
asked me why
so many people
upset because
boats? These people
come here and
are working. This is good.
for the economy.
Wait, so Rishi
Did Sunak tell you this?
Of course, yes. He
told me this when
was chancellor.
When Rishi Sunak was
Chancellor, he said
: "I don't understand why
people are upset because
boats. These people
come here and
are working".
Yes.
Ovva. This is extremely
strange words.
And therefore, and...
Well, it's not just about
Rishi. Your argument in
because he thinks so
majority
Conservative
parties.
This is the majority.
Conservative
parties, of course.
So, they
adhere to
liberal views
for immigration. And this
spreads further,
because they
consider it in
economic terms
. They believe that
influx of people into
country is useful for
economy. This
liberalism
extends to their
views on
citizenship,
culture and
identity. So
they occupy
uncontrolled, "everything
allowed",
liberal position
about who can
to call oneself
English and
British. And if you
here for a while,
maybe born
here, then you... Everyone is welcome.
Everyone is invited. And this
...it's not because of evil
intentions. I think this is
comes from the desire "numo"
all together
"Let's unite" in this
joint project
unity. Reality,
however, is that,
that it is completely
denies the existence
ethnic, cultural
and generic
differences in our
country. And also this
denies my
Asian heritage, as
a person similar to
me. Why should I be
forced to take over
Englishness as
ethnicity or
identity if
this is not in mine
blood? I don't have any.
of English blood. As
stated in the book, I
worked with
historian over his own
pedigree, so that
fill in the details on
beginning of this book.
My roots are in India,
in Mauritius, in Kenya
through Mozambique. There is
a little Portuguese
blood. This is real
mixture, but there is no
nothing English.
And the connecting link is
Britishness. This
link—British
empire. My ancestors
were subject to
British Empire.
They fought side by side.
side by side with the British.
They worked with
by the British. They
built together with
have received an education
thanks to the British.
They received
shelter from
British. Women in
my family is British
were given the right to vote.
They were released.
by the British. There is
very strong
British connection.
And that's why I'm proud
I feel British.
But to say that I
English, it would mean,
as you say,
to reject an entire group
the people of this country and
erase a very important
tribal and ethnic
identity that
associated with England.
Homer wrote two
the most important books in
Western literature.
"The Odyssey" is the one that
recently attracted
to yourself all the attention from
obvious reasons. A "
The Iliad, a work about
pride, rage and
leadership, which is not
less important now
also has
free course
from Hillsdale. New
free online
college course
Hillsdale, which
taught by a professor
Stephen Smith. This is not
collection of basic
moments and not Homer
for beginners. It
thorough study
text about honor,
courage, leadership,
friendship, sacrifice and
what it means to live
noble life. You
you will understand why
real struggle
Achilles is not only
fighting the Trojans,
and the struggle with oneself
yourself. This is one of
over 40 free
courses offered
Hillsdale: about
Constitution, Rome
republic,
American
foundation, Book
Genesis, World War II
war and many
another. All of them
are built the same:
are taught
properly, without
simplifications. I
hard
I recommend courses
Hillsdale.
Go to hillsdale. edu/
trigger to register
free. It
hillsdale.edu/trigger.
One of the things in which
I think you have
unique opportunities
, there is talk about
Britain in
comprehensive way.
I think among so
called "chatterers"
classes" the idea that
that Britain is evil,
became peculiar
generally accepted
thought. This is a kind of
a priori beginning
conversations. Hmm, I think so.
if historians
will write about this
period if Britain
Will he survive this at all?
period, they will say,
that people have gone crazy.
What do you see in
Britain, what
Don't they see?
Well, that's another reason.
why I wrote this
book. I wrote this
a book for those people,
who are tired of
what they are called
far-right
racist
thugs only for
what they say,
like Britain
made a few
good things for
civilization in
past; What
British Empire
actually was, um,
the power of good for
millions, not
billions, people; by
what they celebrate
our heritage, our
culture, um, ours
Christian faith. Ahem
who are tired of
of being called names
fanatics just for that
that they raise
our national
flag. And this book—
challenge that, um,
a consensus that
says that Britain and
everything that concerns
British history,
of the British people
and British
culture, there is
racist and evil.
So what exactly is in
Is Britain great?
We need to stand up and
challenge this.
And um, what's great about
Britain? Well, from our
historical
prospects like me
laid out in a book,
British Empire,
yes, of course there were
mistakes made and
were, um,
unjustified offenses
, but there was also
immeasurable good. Ahem,
was also immeasurable
good, done
thanks to the British
investments,
British risk,
the British contribution,
British service,
um, in particular
completion and
the abolition of slavery.
Um, and
industrialization and
development of whole
parts of the country.
Mauritius is wonderful.
example. This is actually
was abandoned
jungle outpost, gm
, before the arrival
British. French
were there, they
laid some
important basics, they
began development and
The formation of Mauritius
; but the British, you know
, gave him a rocket
acceleration, and he
became one of
the largest countries-
sugar producers, hm,
or islands in the world
until the middle of the 20th
century thanks to
British
innovations,
industry and
ingenuity. And um,
this is just one example.
Kenya—another one
example.
Infrastructure,
schools, law
systems,
democratic systems
—all this has been implemented
by the British. And this,
you know, little ones
examples of the role that
Britain played in
world history, —
why schools don't
devote enough
attention in class and what about
young people are going out
in the world, not at all
knowing. Um, and I just
I think that with
historical
prospects, but
also from a cultural perspective
prospects. I
I'm telling you about mine.
education, and it is in the classroom
I really am
fell in love with Britain.
It is thanks to my
teachers who
opened for me
the beauty of the great
English
literature, wonderful
British anthems,
told about our
war heroes, in particular
during the Second
World War II, my
the heart is full
enthusiasm and
in gratitude for that
Britain made for
world and continues
to do by setting
quality standards,
justice,
of decency—all those
great values,
which we cherish. But
if you say about
this out loud, you
will be perceived as
some kind of warlike
tavern grumbler
, which is waving "
"Union Jack" is,
you know,
right-wing radical
thug. It
does not reflect at all
of what, in my opinion,
, silent believes
the majority in our
country.
You know, that's interesting. We
with my four-year-old
son rode the train
to London, and for some reason—
I promise you, it's not
my washing
brains. He went to
one of the tourist
shops in London
during the previous
trips and demanded,
so that I can buy it for him
most
British flag,
who was there. So here it is
he, four years old
baby walking around
. Well, I didn't have to
none of this
relationship, honestly speaking
.
Future Radical
is growing.
Yes, that's right. He-
far-right.
Yes, yes, yes. Its
can be expelled from
schools for this.
On the train literally
everyone who passed by
passed by and looked at
him, sincerely
smiled, it was me
noticed. People were
very happy to see
a little boy
with British
flag. I think that
vast majority
people just don't
perceives the world in this way
way. Therefore for me
It is extremely strange that
media and elite discourse
so
distorted in relation to
ordinary
citizen.
M-hm. In this book I
I call for decisive action.
our restoration
cultural
confidence in
Britain, because, on
in my opinion, among
most people
silence reigned
complacency about
the virtues of Britain,
Britishness, ours
history and culture;
but now this
abuse
immigration, people who
come to our
countries and do not want
good for her, and also
elite, establishment,
"luxury class"
beliefs", quoting
Rob Henderson. Hmm, eh
-eh, people in general are leftists
views that through
this is adhered to
prejudiced opinion that
looking at Britain
and British
identity in very
in a negative light,
claiming that others
culture somehow
way higher than
British way
life that we should
dodge
inside out, no
to look racist,
not to protect and not to
to keep our
actually, and what, you know, "
"Fortress Britain" is
very bad condition
the things we have
spread red
the path before others
cultures, to become
on your knees in front of
others, even if
they are causing us
damage, and what we have
to appease them,
frankly speaking,
to appease our
enemies. And, um, I
I think that this
elitist and
marginal view,
which penetrates our
institutions through
a kind of "wok"-
leftist ideology, and I
I think it's harmful,
this really kills
people. This is actually
kills people because
because of this they appear
things like plans
actions against racial
questions to the police and
the BLM movement, which says, um,
that we shouldn't
stop and
to search people,
because we
institutionally
racist, and, um, what
we must provide
black preference
before the whites. AND,
you know, terrible
the way in which
treated Henry
Novak. The way those
police
behaved on the spot,
originates from
all of this
cultural
deformation, about which
you are talking.
So, moving on
, Suello, you are now in
"Reform" party, and "
The "reform" is experiencing
difficult times, aren't they?
Yes? There were scandals,
financial scandals,
Sunday Times exposé.
What do you think about this?
as a person who is
within the party?
Well, thank God for "
"Reform" is all I
I can say. I
felt high
level of despair,
political
disorientation and
real
homelessness
after 2023, when
came to you on
conversation. As I already
I said I didn't have faith.
to the Conservative
party, and I—
patriotic, grateful
to all those patriots, and
I want to feel
confidence in
political party,
who is not afraid to be
patriotic. Ahem,
Simply put, what
don't be afraid to do it
the necessary work to
to secure our
borders, for the sake of
all that is holy. What
will not appease
Islamists. What will it be?
to arrest, um,
gangs of groomers, not
to turn a blind eye to them
out of fear of giving up
racists. Hmm, what
actually going
ban the IRGC,
rather than letting them
to enter the country and
to tear it apart
pieces. So I
I feel great.
gratitude for that "
"Reform" exists. And, um,
I will accept any.
challenge. I would rather choose
10 difficult days in "
"Reform" with all those
scandals that they
They throw knives at us.
one day in
Conservative
party, because the party "
Reform"
is determined by trust
. This is what she has.
Nigel Farage and all,
who is in "Reform", here
not for the sake of status,
titles or image.
They are here to do
that's right, and that's it
really gives me
hope. These are people who...I
met a lot of people
over the last 9 months,
since I joined the party,
people who nominated
their candidacies for
local elections.
I am really impressed.
one thing. They are not
career politicians.
The People's Army—we
now the biggest
political party in
country. People who
join the "
"Reforms" are those who
never been before
politically active.
Many people have never
voted. They
thought it was nothing
doesn't change that there is no
meaning. But there's something about them
woke up.
Something is happening,
what are you talking about, and
many of these
people instead of
to go out
streets with anger,
join the "
"Reforms", because they see in
this is the last chance
save Britain, and
I confirm this, this is
That's right.
I never thought that
I will become the one who
will change your mind
about underwear, and
Here I am on the political stage.
podcasts I'm going to
do exactly that. I
I'm talking about Sheath, S-H-E-A-T-H
, sheath.com. This is underwear.
linen, built
on the system
double bag.
If in simple language,
this means that everything
stays on his own
places. None
adhesions, none
rubbing, none
poking around in the middle
sentence, trying
keep serious
appearance. The fabric breathes
, design divides.
Apparently, there is
technical term for
of what it creates, and
this term—"Zen-
distribution", which sounds
It's absurd, but it is.
quite accurate. Its
developed by a veteran under
time for your second
services, which means
that it was created
in conditions where comfort
was not a luxury.
Over 10,000
five-star
feedback from people,
who are not joking, and,
honestly, the difference
in my
everyday
comfort is greater than
I am comfortable.
to discuss on
political podcast
. Who knows, that
will understand. Go ahead.
at sheath.com. This is s-h-e-a-t-h.com.
Use the code
trigonometry at
design
order for
receive a 20% discount.
The first pair is valid
full warranty
refund,
so there is no reason not to
try. sheath.com.
Having tried Sheath alone
once, you are no longer
you will want to come back
to another. sheath.com.
Listen, the problem is
because of the past
week came out
YouGov survey,
according to which year
because 27% of voters
were going to vote
for "Reform". Now
this figure dropped to 22%. AND
I think, I think that
financial scandals
played their part in this
role. People were watching.
to this they said: "Is
they are just another one
political party? Or
a party of dirt and
scandals?"
The answer is no. I, I
I think, you know, myself
Nigel, if he were here
sat down, would be the first
admitted that we are a new
party. So we
are developing, and we are in
in the process of enlargement
and professionalization
. And, you know, will there be
sometimes happen
any errors? Yes,
Of course, they will. You, you
you will see progress on
this moment. You know,
It is now autumn 2026,
in just two years from 2024-
progress was
exponential. AND
you could say, well,
you know, "Reform" is a bit
were mistaken with
selection of candidates
in 2024, because our
processes, well, there were
immature. All this
the work was done,
and now everything
fixed. And we
we have very, very
quality candidates,
which pass through
strict selection. And I
very, I am very
excited about the group
people who
will put forward their
nominations from us
on the following
general elections.
Brilliant, talented
people who have
experience beyond borders
politics. You know,
regarding financing, we
never been, well,
a new party, and yet
yes, in 2 years we
provided record
, the largest donations
in political history.
You know, this
phenomenal. So I
I think this is great.
vote of confidence, but
also, you know, we
we are developing. And therefore
And we too
we are very opposed
hostile media, because yes
just like you say about
these elites
establishment, that
leftist, well, bourgeois
mainstream, which
is set on
believes in open
borders and what
Britain is evil, that's it
the very group of people who
believes that "Reform"—
This is bad news. AND
they will do everything,
to try
stop "Reform".
They have been for years
tried to call
us racists. They
saw that it was not
It works very well. Now
they are trying
to say that we
corrupt. This is not
will work. They
are trying
adjust the rules
under yourself. They
are trying to change,
they are trying
change the rules regarding
donations. So they
they want to do, they
make us...
Sorry to interrupt.
, but I think that this
important point. You
you say that it is not
will work, but I think
what is Francis's opinion in
because it is
It worked.
Well, we haven't had it yet.
elections. Let's see what
will happen during
May elections. It
the only way
to find out.
You know, getting
Reform Party 100
places on the following
the elections would be
stunning
result,
historically
unprecedented.
Obtaining "Reforms"
» 40 seats instead
there would be five
amazing. But
the problem is that
if you say that this
last chance
save the country, that is
will not lead you to
power, and now you are not
you have a chance
to form a government.
Well, I actually think
that these surveys are not
reflect what
I see. You know, I...and
again, I have
to say that some
sociological
companies do not
necessarily
behave properly
in a way. I think they
underestimate support
"Reforms". I think
they overestimate the other
support. Certain
parts of mainstream
media is exactly that
do. So I don't
convinced that
says one group
surveys. There is also
and other surveys,
which show absolutely
other. So the results
surveys constantly
are changing.
There are also markets
forecasts, Swell,
which show that
support
Conservative
party is growing. Now
observed
a certain exaltation.
Let's see how long this lasts.
will continue, but we
we also need to evaluate
the influence of the "Reforms". This, I
I think it's impossible.
to deny
Well, I mean, I
I'll say it again...This is what
I tell people the truth.
views. Next
There will probably be elections.
, the most important
general elections
in my life. And the choice
will be very, very
clear. We will
to choose between
continuation
socialism, a certain
coalition of the left
parties. And this means
more poverty,
more taxes,
more immigration,
more weakness, and
after another five years
socialism situation
can become
irreversible. Or are we
we can start
update and
fight back.
And only "Reforms"
can win
Labour. So
I appeal to everyone.
right-wing, to those
conservatives, to whom
likes Kemi, and
who thinks: "Oh, I
I'm staying on board.
conservatives,
"even when he's drowning"
. You are actually
vote for
socialism. If you
want to stop
Labour, if you
socialist
the destruction of our
countries, there is no time for
nostalgia. None
time for sentimentality
regarding the Conservative
parties. No time for
emotions about
Conservative
parties. It is the "Reforms"
» is the only party,
which has a real chance
to win
Labour. If you
thought: "Well, you
like Rupert
Lowe. Do you like it?
his character and you
do you think it
real
professional. You
you don't live in reality
world. They can't
to win. Therefore,
whatever idealists
you were not the only one
way to stop this
disaster—this
vote for "
Reform". Therefore, it has
unification to take place
around the "Reform".
Conservatives do not
can win in
Wales. They just
is not promising
by force. They have 120 seats.
They need more.
than double this
result to have
at least some chance. As
they are going to do this
make? In Wales they
end. They only have
a handful of places in
Scotland. Northern
Midlands strip, "
"red wall", which
brought Borys to
Downing Street, disappeared
. They are no longer
vote for
conservatives. They
reduced to
to reclaim only
wealthy areas
London and surrounding areas
counties This is not
formula for success. This is not
the path to victory. So
if your goal is—
defeat socialism
and save the country,
it should be "Reform".
Someone might say:
if your goal is—
to defeat socialism,
then the right-wing forces have
unite.
And I would say that this
actually the same thing, about
That's what I said. I think
all those right-wing voters
orientations that
interested in
restoration...
You understand that I
meant. I didn't have
I mean the word......
conservatives. I
I understand. In the end, I
was myself
conservative 30
years. Me
it took a lot
time to break up
connections, and many in
why was it because
relationship. I am finally
fell out of love with the National
party. For me it is
it was obvious. But
very personal
relationships with people,
which I had
for decades,
They held me. They are like
family. These were people from
my district. These were
my mom and dad,
for the sake of everything
saint. My mother
was an advisor from
Tories. She
ran for office
parliament. You see,
It's in my blood.
family. The gap itself
these connections
held me back, and I
I think the same.
happens with
many people who
still in
Conservative
parties. They are not
may dare
to upset one's own
friends or, you know,
change the command, by
essence. I think so.
respectable and
understandable, but
The future of the country is at stake.
The future is at stake
our children, and if you
want to save
country, you must
to put realism
above emotions, therefore
they have
unite around "
Reforms".
But doesn't it seem
what is it worth to you
to show a little
realism? Look,
simple truth
is that I,
personally, always
got along well with
Nigel. Me
I like Nigel.
The problem is that
Nigel is like Marmite:
either like it or
No. There are people who are all
life voted for
conservatives, for
which Nigel is
too. That's how it is.
there are such people
a lot. But there are others, and
there are more and more of them,
radicalized
crisis with small
boats that say: "
In fact, Reform is too
soft-bodied. To us
need a harder one
approach. Desperate
times require
desperate measures
". So the question we
actually put
to you, Suella, or
Will you be able to work?
together? Because I
I look at the left and
I think: "They will be
work together." AND
if you don't—we're in
in a difficult situation.
I don't...I mean,
Listen, I have to
mind...
You know what? You
you express the right
thoughts. You know, this
That's nice to hear, right?
Listen, I'm sincere.
I feel that if you
read that book,
then you will see that
Conservative
parties simply do not
can be trusted.
The face is different, but
the family is the same, and
ways to promise and
lie the same. And that's it.
this is just for the sake of
pictures. All for the sake of
of what looks like
okay, for the sake of
surveys and
lobby groups, but
This is all insincere, that's all.
performance. They are very
good at speeches.
They are very good at
press conferences.
political show. But
behind all this—a solid
imitation. And that's why
I am so grateful to the party.
Reform and Nigel. They are in
This is not for show.
Nigel spoke about
migration crisis
for decades, even before
how it happened
mainstream, before
as columnists of The Times
agreed with him. And for
that's what they called him
racist and as soon as
didn't name it, but he
continued. He was
the first to say that
European Union
destroys our
democracy. For this
establishment
tried it
stop. But he doesn't
surrendered. And I think that
this requires
special courage
and resilience, which
now unique for
British politics
. All these policies are like this
fake. They are like this
superficial, they
just follow
the latest trends,
want to jump in
the last car to
to go up a little in
surveys,
to get into
newspaper headlines or
to receive approval
material. But this is not
real, and I saw
This is close up. I saw
this is on the example of Rishi. I
saw it with Kemi, with
Boris, with Cameron.
It's all just a show, and
I will say this:
Conservative Party
—it's like an unfaithful
partner. He is constantly
breaks your heart with
other women, and
then returns with
flowers and a box
sweets and says: "Darling,
I'm sorry, I really am.
I'm sorry. "I have changed"
. "I don't do that anymore."
"I will." You forgive.
him, and he again
takes on the old. AND
you are blaming yourself for
that I forgave. That
constantly does
Conservative Party
. I have changed. I am more
I won't do that. I promise.
But they do it.
again. Reform Party
"—it's like that guy,
which passed through
fire for you.
He is a little beaten and
exhausted, but he
real, because it will pass
through the swamp for the sake of
you and what will make you
necessary. He will say
what is necessary. He
he says this sincerely
hearts, and he was right
. That's why there is "
Reform". This is true.
the heart of the country, and
Nigel—no
apostate. He is not
changed his views.
He did not follow
fashion. Here is who
attracts "Reform".
She attracts people,
who have sincerity
spirit and do not chase after
titles, status or
by power. He is real.
. And so, are there certain "
"growing pains" and whether
need something
fix? Of course.
Of course. That's what we are.
we do, and the party
professionalizes
very quickly. But
the foundations have already been laid.
And the British people
sees it. Well, about
Nigella, this is what I'm talking about.
that often bothers me
people ask. I
I answer: what would you
didn't think about him,
the only thing he doesn't have
can be blamed—
it's that he's in
politics for the sake of
money, because he is very
earned well in the City
, and then left
to run for office,
lost the deposit and
just promoted very much
an unpopular cause,
because he believed in her. It's me.
I understand, but Suella,
You are a smart woman. You
You know what we're talking about.
we ask. I have on
in mind, if we talk
realistic, that is
high probability,
what about the next
elections, despite your
a beautiful story about
the wrong guy and
everything else, a lot
people will stay with
Conservative
party. Maybe their
there will be little. It
could be 40, 50 or 100
places, and they
you need for
formation of the government.
So, the question is,
Will there be a "Reform"?
if this happens or
even before that
ready for something
electoral agreement, or
after the fact
to unite in
in the interests of the country and
say: "Okay, this one
the guy is not very good
reliable, but we are
"to the authorities." They are
junior partner in
this coalition. We
we can implement
our agenda,
because, as you yourself say,
the alternative is
socialism.
No deals. None
agreements.
Do you prefer
socialism than an agreement
with conservatives?
Return to
work with
fundamentally
dishonest partner?
How can you do this?
make? It's like, "Oh,
okay, I just
I will close my eyes to everything.
your previous ones
misdemeanors, on your
history of chronic
lies."
This is getting a bit long.
personal.
I hit a sore spot.
?
No, not really. But
I feel guilty.
just because of how you
file this case.
Don't worry. As yours
lawyer, I advise you
not to answer
none of these
accusations.
Um, yes, how could we
to do this? In them, in
their, their, their hands
not clean. How can you
, they are
But then you yourself
bring socialism closer
, to whom yes
resist.
What do I tell people? I
I think the choice, as I already
said it would be
understandable, it will be
clearer for people
during the elections.
Now it's more
vaguely, because,
you know, people
everyone is considering
options, and they haven't yet
need to be decided.
But I think when
the mind will focus,
you know, on the elections
precincts, then I think,
that the choice will be very
very clear.
Good. We are quite
you were put under a lot of pressure
in this matter. THERE ARE
one thing I'm talking about
I always ask people.
from your party when
you come to us. AND
I think that this
actually very
important question. I am not
I hear a lot about this.
talked. I see how
Robert Jenrick, yours truly
economic expert,
talks about it a little
more. But to me
it seems that for "
Reforms" exists
a big challenge,
because I think that
your guidance
parties, including you
, probably when the language
it's about the economy,
advocates for—I would
I imagined, correct me,
if I'm wrong, you
Do you think taxes
too high. You
Do you think that business
limited
regulation, etc. You
Do you think the economy
depressed and her
need to be revealed.
Too much government,
too much interference,
too much of everything
this. Too much
social
software. And so
further. Aha.
But at the same time, many
people who come
to your party, there is
leftists in economics.
They want
redistribution, they
want a powerful
social security system
protection, they want
NHS, they want everything
of what
The British are already used to it.
And that seems quite
a difficult task for
implementation. Because
British
public left in
economic issues
, and you—no.
People watching
this show, usually
more thoughtful
on how they work
governments than most
others. But there is a difference.
between understanding
problems and
creating a real
protection from it. It
the world in which it works
Mikkel Thorup. He
already living as an emigrant
over 25 years old,
visited over 110
countries and in nine of
They managed to live.
Almost ten years
that's why he founded Expat
Money to help
others to do the same.
When he helps
to create for someone
international plan "B",
the knowledge it provides,
is exclusively from its own
experience. Each
recommendation
is based on the fact that
which he has already done himself.
Expat Money works specifically with
freedom-loving families
and investors who
want to reduce their
dependence on
one government or
one system. Second
residency, second
citizenship,
offshore banking
accounts, international
real estate,
legal structures,
that distribute your
life across borders.
Mikkel prepared
free report
under the title "
Residencies and
instant citizenship
"according to plan B." In it
five are considered
ways to get
second passport,
including one, about
which almost never
they say. As a foreign
residency is working
like the real thing
political
insurance, which
countries really have
meaning depending on
what are you trying to do
to protect, and how much
it really costs.
Go to
expatmone.com/trigger or
click the link
in the description of this episode
to download
report. It's free,
without guile. It
expatmone.com/trigger.
British
public left in
economic issues
, and you—no.
Hmm, I would argue that
most people who
come to us, there are
leftists in economics.
Yes, we are winning in
many former
Labour strongholds,
which in the past
elections
voted for
conservatives. Um, we
we win, we
we show very
good results in
places like
Wales, Essex,
Norfolk, Suffolk and,
you know, in
industrial
centers. Um, but I would
denied the fact that
that these people are leftists. I would
said that they,
perhaps historically
were voters
Labour. Hmm, but
they want lower
taxes. These are people who
there is, you know,
representatives
working class, which
want to receive
more than that they
earn. Hmm, this is
people who see, um,
uncontrolled
social benefits, um
, billions of pounds,
spent on
illegal
migrants, eh,
suppression of wages
due to the tide
foreign
employees, and, um,
they are tired of
this. Um, I, I met
there are many such people in
to one's own
district, actually
. Um, just a few
weeks ago I met
man of years
thirty-something,
apparently. He was
decorator painter.
I met him when
he was just returning
home, and he said
me: "You know, I
actually fed up
throat and angry. THERE ARE,
My wife just...
We have one child, and
She is sitting at home with
a baby. I work.
almost 6-7 days
week. We were not in
I've been on vacation for 2-3 years now.
We want another one
child, but we have
there is none
opportunities to allow
have another child. AND
I'm so angry at this government.
exhausts and breaks me
, and the tax rate
It just suffocates. THERE ARE,
the cost of mine
materials and labor
became...She never
was higher. And as I have,
you know, to keep
a small child and
wife? And I'm here.
I'm doing everything right.
I am teaching here on
full and not sitting on
help, and such
feeling that
British state
does everything to,
you know, substitute
Give me a foothold. And I
I think millions
people feel that
exactly, and they are completely
could have been historically
voters
Labour. Therefore,
it all comes down to
tax cuts.
Tax burden
too high, and
that's why we
spoke with a very
big political
statement. Robert
Jenrick announced on
conferences that we
let's raise the threshold
personal privilege, um,
up to 15,000 pounds
sterling for those, uh,
those who have, uh, lower
earnings, and this, uh,
will lead to the fact that
people will leave
more money from
their earnings. But
tax thresholds are
very good example
of how the past
conservative government,
supposedly a party
low taxes,
completely failed.
You know, these tax
the thresholds were
frozen in time
pandemics, although they
promised to raise them,
but not so far
arrived. Another one
Tory lies. But this
really distorted
our system
personal
taxation. Therefore,
you have people with low
income that never
shouldn't have been
pay higher rates
tax, but they go there
dragged in. So I would
said that these people
really want
lower taxes, and
lower taxes—that's not
...Absolutely, for sure. AND
here is the classic
an example of how we
a punitive one appeared
tax system. It
does not stimulate people
work. Ago
many people think: "Well,
actually I could
earn more on
help "." Why
I have to work if
to get help
so easy? "So, this is
is getting longer and longer
more people on
low-paid
work. Besides
teachers and nurses,
who never had
pay a higher rate,
now they pay her. AND
regarding higher incomes,
well, you know,
marginal tax
The rate is punitive. THERE ARE
people who are not
will agree to
increase, not
will work harder
hours, because it's just not
Is it worth their time?
money. So how do we
created such
personal information system
taxation, which
actually repels
people from work and
restrains them? If this is
is not a sign
inoperable system
, then I don't know what then.
Therefore, I will say that these
people really want
lower taxes, and
lower taxes—that's not
...
I'm just looking at
the popularity of such
things like tax on
luxury, and everything
this...I never
used the expression "
"politics of envy",
but in many ways it is
similar to VAT on
private education
schools. This is just
led to the fact that
the rich continue
to send their
children to private
schools, and people who were
on the verge of barely
scraped together the funds for
private education,
now forced
to transfer children to
public schools that
worsens the situation in
the last ones because
increase in number
students in classes, etc. AND
it's just politics,
which says: we have all become
a little poorer, so
let's "press"
those who have a little
more. And these measures
are becoming quite
popular in the country.
That's right.
Well, I would say that we
we believe...So, we
we believe in the system
social
provision for
all vulnerable persons
and those who really don't
can work, and we
We care about these people.
But we have a system,
which is no longer
is determined
real
vulnerability and
a real need. IN
we have a system that
actively demotivates
work. We have
a system that works
too soft. And therefore in
there are too many of us,
who claim that
they are sick or
incapacitated, and not
can work,
although in reality
can.
So what are you going to do with this?
What should I do, Rachel?
Well, the party
suggested
large-scale reforms
social sphere. We
we will assess the condition
much better health
stricter. We
we will reduce expenses on
social
software
about 50
billions of pounds. It
significant savings.
We will direct these funds to
things like defense
or other areas of our
economies that
really need
investments. We are the only one
the party that
offered enough
bold plan
social reforms
software.
You will be
to accuse, as it were
was with Duncan
Smith, in that you,
you know, you're causing
harm to people, perhaps
even bring them to
death. And through
the bulkiness of these
huge state
systems, unfortunately, if
have you ever
reduce aid
people with a diagnosis
ADHD, anxiety or
something like that,
it turns out that some of
they really were in
in a difficult situation
and needed
support. How are you?
are you going to cope?
with all this?
And this again, you
you know, there are many
lessons that can be
to learn from experience
conservatives. They
tried to hold
social reform
provision, but not
gone far enough
far away, because for their
board volume
payments only increased.
Labour Party
—very good
an example of this.
It seems that everyone
Prime Minister of
Labour
tries
reduce costs for
social security, but
there are about a hundred
Labor-
backbenchers,
who are strongly against
this will not be allowed
This is what will happen. So,
hmm, I doubt that
Andy Burnham will reach
at least some progress
in cost reduction
on social
help. Therefore I
I think this is...Here
why am I so glad that
there is a party "Reform"
". You know, among us
is political
consistency. Again
yes, that's one of the reasons
why I am very happy
to be in "Reform". You
you know, you said
about the invasion. I
said that this
invasion when there was
Minister of the Interior
affairs. It seems that in 2022
or 23 years old. Deputies-
Tory, you know,
lost their minds,
panicked and
They said I was sowing.
disagreement, the tone is wrong
, the rhetoric is wrong, and,
you know, me, um,
criticized their own
colleagues, including
cabinet members. Ahem,
everyone in the party" Reform
"consider it
invasion and very,
hmm, comfortable
feel,
describing it exactly like this.
The same applies to
such things as
social reform
software. Ahem,
you know, it will be
party. We already are.
party, and we
we will stay
party, which, you
you know, united in
on this issue, therefore
what we all see
the scale of the problem and
urgent
necessity
reduce these costs,
because otherwise nothing
impossible to do.
Economic growth
impossible for
current state
social spending
software. Ahem,
invest in our
defense is impossible,
if we continue
to spend so much
on social security.
Um, you know, this is before
how we get to
schools and hospitals. Therefore,
it is economical
priority number one,
if we are going
reduce taxes and
to launch an economic
growth.
One interesting
moment regarding your
theses on disagreements
and statements
certain things in a certain way
Time is what we have.
former guest Matthew
Sayed, whom we
we love to see in
on air. He wrote
article in The Times this
week, where he said that
Matthew is great because he
skillfully
turns to his
kind of center
British politics
, and people of the left
views also his
are listening. But he
as if saying what people
like you
only 5, 6 or 10 spoke
years ago. He
wrote an article in
which actually
claims that Angels
Merkel, David
Cameron, Macrons
of this world, they
were extremists,
while they were being glorified.
And it seems more and more
that consensus, or
suddenly a window
Overton, shifts
so fast. And now
more and more people
receive permission
to believe in things that
we argued
a long time. Or
Do you see this?
opportunity for
"Reform" party
really win
the next elections as
the result of this?
I think more
people...I think you
you're right, window
Overton is shifting.
But I also think that
more people are becoming
increasingly
more desperate.
It arises stronger
feeling of despair
because of what to do with
various crises that
are affecting our country.
And in many ways, than
it gets worse
Labour, and for
this government
there will be more Labor members
worse. The budget will be
disaster. Quite
it is possible that during
the next 12 months in
this country will come
financial crisis.
Immigration will be
to deteriorate. Will be
more riots.
There will be more
protests. Will be
more than two-stage
police system
. There will be more
Islamism. Victims
grooming gangs are not
will receive justice
. You know, with each
the year when our
the country is increasingly
slides down,
level of despair,
fear and anger
is growing. And I think that
again, exactly
so I am very grateful
to be in a party that
fearlessly offers
your decisions. We
the only party that
says: "We are actually
militarize our
border. We will use
Royal
naval
fleet". Conservatives
They make fun of this, but
actually it is
the right way. I
was in Greece when
held office
Minister of the Interior
affairs. Greece is
relative history
success when it comes to
about the fight against
illegal
migration. At the peak
problems with
Syrian
million refugees
migrants, you know,
invaded Greece
through its sea
border. They
built a wall.
The Greeks actually
built a wall on
to his land
border with Turkey.
They used
drones, armored vehicles
and soldiers, and for
several years
the number has decreased
by approximately 90%. That
you can see it too
in the case of America.
You know, decisive.
approach to security
borders was that
helped stop
problem on
the southern border. AND
I think people...more
a few years ago
they would consider
unthinkable attraction
armed forces for
protection of our
borders, but now,
I think more and more
people agree,
that this is necessary
West. And "Reform"—
the only party that
says: "Yes, we agree."
This is exactly what we
we offer in our
politics.
Before we move on
until our last
questions and
questions from our
audiences for Substack, there are
something I always think about
...this is the question I
I always put
politicians of any kind
direction: how are you
When do you think they will be?
the following general
election?
Actually, I would like to
to find out what you are
you think. This is yours.
kind of...well, lottery. You
must...we must...
Wait, like the mayor in
program" Off the Fence ", this
new show that we
launched from
Winston Marshall
and Tom Slater from
Spike. So we are constantly
Let's discuss this.
Yes. What is your position?
Yes. So, here's how...
if I were Burnham, I
would announce them in
the next couple
months. I believe that
this is the best time for
him. And I know...I
I know, Andy, you love
This is a show, so...
Yes.
You know, advice from
me to you.
Did you have it?
No, no, no.
Did you invite him?
Of course. We invite
all leaders
major parties.
You know, he...he's from
the same part of the world,
as is my father. So in
we have a lot in common,
Andy. Ahem. I say if
he was smart, he
I would do it now.
He will never be
more popular than
now. He has this one.
lift. He hasn't yet
managed to implement
a policy that will
to annoy, to anger and
alienate certain
people. It seems that for
"It is a certain impulse."
The reform "suffered"
from scandals and
another. So now
they are in decline.
The right did not unite.
Green as if
retreated because
he...he is very
skillfully done with
ultra-left in
Labor
parties. This should be
the moment when he
will do it now. It
really annoying
b some members,
some deputies from
Labor
parties, because they
will lose their places.
But if it
the ultimate goal—
leave Labour
in power, I think,
he should do it
now. Personally, I don't
I think that's him.
will do. I think he
thinks that he has
enough support,
to hold out longer
two or three years.
Of course.
Yes, and I mean,
the idea that he
it will never be like this
popular as it is now,
I think it's quite
Okay. The only question
in that he could
to declare elections
now and lose or
be obliged
to create a coalition,
which would make it difficult for him
life. So he can
just wait. It
maybe so, you know,
you know what you
you will get...But also,
you know, we
argued about it on
Off The Fence program
the other day. Maybe we
We now live in the country.
, where most
votes for the left. I
I am speaking purely.
statistically, regarding
percent of people. I think
, Winston noted that
we constantly
let's argue about it,
but the percentages
remain
absolutely unchanged
. 47 for the left, 47 for
right-wing. Uh, and Burnham,
it seems very, very
skillfully consolidates
left-wing electorate. So,
when it comes to
voting, they
they say, "You know what? We
must stop "
Reform". We must
stop Farage." And
they all gather and
vote for the left
party. Uh, so it's hard.
say. Uh, but he
recently stated himself,
what will not happen, he will not
will appoint
election. What do you think?
Is that so? You to him
Do you believe?
Well, all the prime ministers
ministers say this
before
to call elections.
It seems Rishi said
on March 24th:"No,
"There will be no elections."
In 3 months we have
There were elections. Uh,
It seems Theresa May
famously said:
Choose me as leader,
I will not appoint
elections ". Literally
in a year she
called elections.
So I never believe
them when they say"
no ". Uh, and, of course, in
there are, you know,
absolute
prerogative regarding them
destination, so
only they
will know. Uh, we
ready. In our party
"Electoral Reform"
state, and we, you know, we
ready for the future
struggle. Uh, and if
he will appoint them,
You know, uh, so be it.
Uh, no one is for him.
voted. And people
really feel, huh
-eh, they feel it keenly,
what is missing
legitimacy. Um, he
...It seems he wants
to declare enough,
you know, big changes
in politics, that
differ from
manifesto. Its
possibilities regarding
tax changes
limited by the manifesto.
He talks about
changes in the field
social protection.
He is very
is concerned about this
question. You know,
this actually
not in the manifest, and
that would be huge
a change in how we
we finance
social protection and
how we provide it.
He wants to do this.
similar to the system
The NHS, essentially. Hmm, this is
big departure from
what they talked about
to people when they were elected
Labour. So, with
On the one hand, he can
to reject the possibility
early elections
in the near future. But
on the other hand, he
speaks about
political steps that,
technically speaking,
would demand elections and
personal
mandate, if he
wanted to implement them.
So, he says
ambiguous, what is...
It's almost as if he
politician. It's almost like that,
like he's a politician, yeah.
I work on a budget.
that the elections
will take place in
the next 6 months.
Really?
Personally, I
interesting. And how are you?
How much do you think?
will receive Reform on these
elections?
Well, I...
Many good ones
results, because, as I
already said, you know,
if you get 100
places—it's amazing.
This is incredible.
Yes, but this
not enough to
to form a government. IN
British politics
, the new party receives
100 seats.
Yes.
Well, I mean,
I think the Reform party
has already reached many
championships for the last
years. So anything is possible.
I mean that
I work on the basis of calculation,
that after the following
general elections
Prime Minister
Farage will become. It
the only way
restore hope and
trust in the country and
to start, you know,
restoration,
frankly speaking, because
the country is in
deep, deep
crisis. Economy
terrible, as we just
noted. Problem
migration is required
solve. You know,
our schools
need
correction, and this is mine
sphere. People can't
to attend a reception
to the therapist. We
completely and
dangerously vulnerable,
when it comes to our
armed forces. We are not
we will be able to protect
ourselves, if only we
attacked by the enemy
state. We...we
crippled. Our heavy
industry
destroyed because of
"pure madness"
zero ". So much for everything
...And I haven't even gotten there yet.
to government dysfunction,
courts and
administrative
state bodies that
simply do not work.
So, you need this
many profound changes,
radical
transformations,
responsible
radicalism. Than
We're faster than that.
Let's do it, the better.
.
Suella, what are we talking about?
We're not talking now, but
would it be worth it?
Before Suella
will respond to
last question,
necessarily
visit triggerpod.co.uk,
where can you do this
see.
What would you change in
police work? Or
What would you do with it?
the police?
What is one thing in
Britain, on your
thought was lost
for your life, and whether
maybe politics
Is it really possible to return it?
What are we not talking about now?
we say, but it's worth it
would it be?
Well, I guess you already
talked about it a little bit
, so maybe it's not
exactly the same answer,
but I'm touching this
in my book, and I
ready for
By the way, you did
book advertising—
book advertising,
book advertising, Tim,
give a name for
listeners. In my
the book "Patriot" I
I say...Continue. «
Patriot: empire,
betrayal and hope." I
I say, and I'm ready for
negative reaction from
female side
community. I
I'm telling you about my
personal experience
starting a family, about
difficulties with
the birth of a child and,
frankly speaking, about
the mistake I made
assumed,
putting it off
too late
term. I gave birth
first child at 39
years, the second—at 40, and,
biologically speaking
language, I almost
I'm late. This is what
I am very interested.
for several years now: no
just my personal one
history, but also the fact that
that I am a part of
a huge phenomenon on
In the West—involuntary
childlessness and
fall
fertility. AND,
actually, for context
, that's pretty good
illustrated in
book. You know, mine
Grandma was born in
1922. She was
one of the nine
children. She came out.
married at 18 and
gave birth to five
children. Three of them
survived. One of them—
my mother. My mother
gave birth to me in 1980
year, and I am an only child
. If we continue
this trend with mine
daughter, she will not have
children. And we won't be able to
to provide a working
force, citizens,
energy, dynamism—
people needed for
support our
countries. This is huge.
social and
economic "bomb"
slow-acting,
which, in fact, already
explodes. We see in
in many parts
world, as governments
are starting seriously
to treat the fall
fertility. And this
what we are talking about
need to start
speak.
And since you're talking about it
they talked, this
really interesting. You
remembered that this is another one
the discussion that I
ignited with their
irresponsible
comments. But
actually we have
will be very interesting
commentators who
will participate in
debates on the show with
about this. What, what
was that? You mentioned,
that you are one of those
the lucky ones who
were able to jump in
the last car, just
on time, at the latest
moment. By the way, this is
has its challenges,
because you have children with
a small difference in
at an age that is not easy, as
we both know,
etc. What exactly
put you in this situation
position? You know what?
that's what made you
to be in such a situation
situation? This is what I
I am researching in my
book. Hmm, I think so.
the most important
This is what I am researching.
in his book. Um, I
I think the most important thing
the reason was that
I was raised
to put academic
and professional
first place achievement
place. Me too
raised to be "
businesswoman." Me
that's how they were raised, and mine
Parents are happy about this.
admit, we often
We are talking about this. They
they told me, and this
follows from experience
my mother and grandmother
: “Don't get married. Not,
Don't get married. Not
Limit yourself. Not
stop at
achieved. Don't let it.
God, don't give birth.
the child too early,
because it will simply destroy
your professional
odds. This will destroy
your career, so
pursue a career." AND
during my 20s
and I am 30 years old
That's what she did. And did
I have it almost perfect,
according to the textbook. AND
then, in my 30s, I
found herself without children and
without a husband, and was
very concerned about
that, perhaps,
made a mistake
and did
wrong choice.
Therefore, I believe that
there is a cultural
question about what
we speak our
young people and our
girls. I don't think so.
what we tell them that
fertility
limited. I don't think so.
that we are enough
we are talking about family in
in a positive way. I
I don't think we
we honor enough
men as dads,
parents and
breadwinners in
our cultural
narratives. And, of course, with
economic point
we have done very
difficult, if not
impossible, for
young people
to start a family and
to think about
marriage or
birth of a child.
You know, if you
finished
university, you
you are starting your journey
with a debt of 50,000
pounds sterling,
when you are a little older
20. Your average
The salary is 35
000 pounds sterling.
You can't possibly do that.
to afford
down payment for
dwelling. Uh, people don't
will give birth
children living in
shared apartments.
Yes.
So, we did
very economical
difficult for young people
people of the establishment
children. Therefore, I believe
that there is a mixture
problems, like
cultural, and
economic, which
contributed to the reduction
fertility.
Uh, Suella, very
Thank you for coming.
show. Hey, welcome.
see. Book
called "Patriot"
, Empire, Betrayal and
Hope". You mentioned her.
only about 73 times
during the interview.
This is not enough. Can
me, can I
remember her again?
Go to
triggerpod.co.uk, where you
you will be able to see it.
If "Reform"
wins parliamentary elections
elections, how are they
will be able to avoid
obstacles from the side
ossified
bureaucracy that
deeply hostile to
reform policies?